Citizens Environmental Coalition; Records apap197
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Citizens' Environmental Coalition Records
1973-2005
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap197
44.25 cubic ft. and 4 videotapes
The records of Citizens' Environmental Coalition (CEC) document its research and activism, from its infancy as part of the New York Environmental Institute, through its independent chartering in 1991, and continuing into the new millennium.
Administrative History
The Citizens' Environmental Coalition (CEC) consists of 110 community and environmental groups and over 14,000 individuals in New York. CEC is active in local, state, and national environmental issues. It operates two offices: the main office in Albany and a Western New York office in Buffalo. CEC's primary purposes are to fight pollution in New York State, build a healthier environment, and to encourage, educate, and organize local citizens with similar goals. It supports democratic, grassroots activities, helps build coalitions, and "promote[s] corporate accountability and non-violent social justice values" ["CEC: About us", Citizen's Environmental Coalition, http://www.cectoxic.org/about.html, accessed 29 March 2006].
The origin of CEC can be traced to "Toxics In Your Community: A Conference To Promote Citizen Involvement" sponsored by the Environmental Defense Fund and the New York State Planners ["Toxics In Your Community: A Conference to Promote Citizen Involvement" brochure, Series 1: Activities, Subseries 12: Toxics, Box 1, Folder 14]. The conference, organized by Gail McFarland Benedict and Anne Rabe, was held at the Silver Bay Conference Center in Silver Bay, NY, October 14-16, 1983. It was the first in a series of successful annual environmental conferences bringing citizens and activists together to fight toxic waste.
Initially named the Toxics In Your Community Coalition, and later known as the Toxics Coalition, CEC obtained support from the New York Environmental Institute (NYEI) in 1985. The Toxics In Your Community Coalition and the Superfund Monitoring Project (SMP) at NYEI facilitated citizen networking and attempted to empower citizens fighting toxic waste in their communities. Activists became cognizant of the difficulties in maintaining citizen participation and one member noted:
One of our purposes stated at the first [Toxics In Your Community] conference was to keep each other informed so that the agencies can't play games with the different groups... If the Coalition is to be a participatory, democratically run group then the local representatives from the toxic sites must make the decision to be active. Otherwise, it becomes another coalition of environmental groups. I believe that is the organizational problem to be solved... [Correspondence from Deborah Wallace, Ph.D., President of Public Interest Scientific Consulting Service to Anne Rabe, Director of the Superfund Monitoring Project, regarding the Toxics In Your Community Coalition, 4 Aug 1985, Series 1: Activities, Subseries 12: Toxics, Box 1 Folder 17].
Several actions were taken to keep ordinary citizens involved. The EPL Institute Inc. ["NYEI 'contracts' with EPL staff to do issue projects.", Statement of Income and Expenses for the New York Environmental Institute 1989-1990, Series 1: Activities, Subseries 12: Toxics, Box 1, Folder 23] published a guide to Effective Citizen Participation in Public Hearings in 1986 [Effective Citizen Participation in Public Hearings, Series 1: Activities, Subseries 12: Toxics, Box 1, Folder 18]. The Superfund Monitoring Project cited "Citizen Assistance" as part of its plan of action in 1987. An early SMP funding proposal indicates: ...many citizens are in rural, isolated communities and face significant opposition to their basic requests for action, such as testing of wells. It is important for them to know their work is valuable and they are not alone. Often, the [Superfund Monitoring] Project helps citizens working on similar site problems to network with each other so they can share ideas and support. The Superfund Monitoring Project regularly receives over 40 calls and letters a week from citizens requesting assistance and information [New York State Superfund Monitoring Project Proposal, Part IV, Section B, May 1987, Series 1: Activities, Subseries 12: Toxics Box 1, Folder 20].
By 1990, the Toxics Coalition became known as Citizens' Environmental Coalition. CEC broadened the fight against pollution and continued to support citizen efforts. It became an independent organization, attaining status as a not for profit, tax-exempt group in 1991.
The leadership of CEC consists of an Executive Committee, a Board of Directors, and an Executive Director located in Albany, NY. A list of the current staff and board of directors is available online at http://www.cectoxic.org/about.htmlhttp://www.cectoxic.org/about.html.
Executive Directors:
Anne Rabe, 1990-2002
Roberta Chase and Kathleen Curtis, 2002-2003 (Acting Co-Directors)
Kathleen Curtis, 2002-present [2006]
Scope and Contents
The records of Citizens' Environmental Coalition (CEC) document its research and activism, from its infancy as part of the New York Environmental Institute, through its independent chartering in 1991, and continuing into the new millennium. The earliest document in the collection is collected research material from 1973. The records in this collection document CEC's growing political maturity through the 1990s, and the bulk of the materials date from that decade.
CEC collection has been divided into eight series: Activities, Administrative Files, Fundraising, Graphics Files, Issue Files, News Clippings, Publications, and Research Material. Environmental issues covered in the collection include (but are not limited to) the following: radioactive waste, Superfund sites, clean drinking water, health care and the environment, agricultural waste, environmental labor concerns, safe schools, the Hudson River, Eastman Kodak, air pollution, toxic waste, and toxic chemicals.
The greatest strength of CEC collection lies in the Activities series. This series documents CEC's plans and actions taken on particular environmental issues. It contains correspondence, outreach files, and research material for numerous activities.
Some records of the Western New York office of CEC are found in the Water subseries. Additional records from that office remain in Buffalo, NY.
The collection also contains records from New York Environmental Institute, EPL Institute Inc., Superfund Monitoring Project, Toxics In Your Community Coalition, Healthy Schools Network, and the Office of Assemblyman Richard N. Gottfried, former New York State Assistant Majority Leader.
This collection lacks comprehensive coverage of all activities. It does not contain a substantial amount of recent records related to persistent toxic chemicals, right-to-know, Superfund, brownfields, and sustainable agriculture. Leadership documents, records listing past members of the board and other leaders, as well as records describing organizational structure (except for 1990-1991), are generally scarce. The collection is not, as of 2006, strong in post-2002 materials.
It should be noted that CEC has frequently re-used paper by printing or copying documents on the reverse side. Examples of this practice include single page outreach letters leftover from mass mailings that were subsequently re-used. Researchers should take care not to confuse the side of the page that was used actively for recordkeeping with the previously used, discarded side. Also, it is helpful to keep in mind that CEC often used both sides of the page when initiating new, longer print jobs such as multi-page reports.
Throughout the collection, researchers will observe frequent changes in institutional name or project name. These name changes can be seen alongside identical institutional addresses, phone numbers, and/or staff names. Changes in name reflect the history of CEC. Researchers should be aware that CEC grew out of the projects of other organizations and that it later joined other environmental coalitions. CEC often acted as a coalition leader, shepherding both individual citizens and citizens' groups.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Subseries 1: Artwork, ca. 1995-2000
Subseries 2: Cartoons, 1977-2000
Subseries 3: Photographs, 1986-2001
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Citizens' Environmental Coalition in May, July, and September 2005 and April 2006.
Related Materials
Several collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives provide further information on the environmental issues of concern to the Citizens' Environmental Coalition. For a complete list of related collections see the subject guide for Conservation and the Environment. Of particular interest are the records of Environmental Advocates of New York (APAP-102), the Sierra Club Atlantic Chapter (APAP-130), and the New York Coalition for Alternatives to Pesticides (APAP-151).
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted except where noted for records related to whistleblowers.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Conservation and the Environment; Air quality--New York (State).; Ecology--New York (State).; Environmentalism--New York (State).; Hazardous wastes--New York (State).; Pesticides--New York (State).; Refuse and refuse disposal--New York (State).; Water quality--New York (State).; Minutes (administrative records); Periodicals; Clippings; Files by subject; Correspondence; Newsletters; Videocassettes; Citizens' Environmental Coalition
- Activities, 1973-2005; 1; 22.35 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of material relating to specific activities of Citizens' Environmental Coalition (CEC). The records in each activity subseries document research, plans, and actions taken to advance an environmental issue in New York State. The subseries dates are not always inclusive. The bulk of the activities date from the late 1980s to the late 1990s, but several folders within each activity subseries contain older information that CEC activists used as background research material.
  This series documents CEC's efforts to support grassroots environmental activities. In some cases, the records demonstrate CEC's efforts to advance an existing grassroots movement. In other examples, CEC's records show it joining state, national, and international networks to become active in a larger environmental cause or project. CEC's records also show extensive outreach activities - efforts to foster cooperation or stimulate new environmental activism among concerned citizens. Limited financial information and budgets are accessible throughout the Activities series, although these tend to be concentrated in a few fiscal years or in specific projects such as publications and conferences. Additional financial records can be found in the Fundraising series.
  Correspondence and reports from government agencies such as the New York State Department of Health (DOH), Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC), United States Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), and others were collected for CEC research. Outgoing correspondence, notes, memoranda, and strategic plans document CEC's efforts to press government regulators to take action. In addition to lobbying material, there are political outreach records.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by subseries.
  - Concentrated Animal Feeding Operations and Sludge, 1983-2003; 1.1; 0.33 cubic ft. and 1 videotape
    This subseries contains publications, papers, reports, guides, pamphlets, and correspondence. The materials relating to Concentrated Animal Feeding Operations (CAFOs) are primarily concerned with environmental and health issues, but also touch on ethics. The materials on sludge are concerned with environmental issues, management, science, and agriculture.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - "Cesspools of Shame", 2000 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 1)
    - "Concentrated Animal Feeding Operations", 1999-2003 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 2)
    - Concentrated Animal Feeding Operations - GRACE, 1983-2001 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 3)
    - Concentrated Animal Feeding Operations / Sludge Project, 2001-2002 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 4)
    - "Corporate Hogs at the Public Trough", ca. 2000 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 5)
    - "Hogging it! Estimates of Antimicrobial Abuse in Livestock", 2000 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 6)
    - "The Jungle 2000: Is America's Meat Fit to Eat?" (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 7)
    - "The Price We Pay For Corporate Hogs", 2000 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 8)
    - Sludge, 1996-2002 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 9)
    - Sludge, Papers and Articles, 1995-2001 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 10)
    - Solid Waste Management, 2000-2001 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 11)
    - WSTB Newsletter, Nitrogen Pollution, Fact Sheet, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 12)
    - "Wasting Away", WSTM Channel 3 Syracuse, News Report, VHS Videotape, ca. 2001; videotape (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 13)
  - Hazardous Waste Sites, 1980-2005; 1.2; 4.5 cubic ft.
    This subseries contains correspondence, notes, reports, and news clippings on hazardous waste sites throughout New York. It includes correspondence and notes documenting CEC activities relating to the sites. Public health assessments put out by the New York Department of Health (DOH), pertaining to the individual sites, are common features of this subseries. It also includes various assessments and reports from the Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC). The folder "New York State Hazardous Waste Site Remedial Program" contains some background information on DOH, DEC, and Department of Law actions relating to these sites, including a map of the nine DEC regions. Most regions contain folders with no individual sites listed on them. These can be considered general folders for that region, and contain materials for various sites that do not have individual folders. Each folder for an individual site generally contains a site name followed by the town or city the site is located in. Most of the sites had clearly indicated DEC region numbers, but the correct region was unclear for a few.
    Arranged by DEC region and alphabetically by site within each region.
    - New York State Hazardous Waste Site Remedial Program, 1990-1995 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 1)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, 1983-1994 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 2)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Brentwood, Hicksville, 1978-1992 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 3)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Brookhaven, 1991-1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 4)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Eugene Dry Cleaners, Babylon, 1992-1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 5)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Garden City Industrial Park Area, Garden City / North Hempstead, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 6)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Genzale Plating Company, Franklin Square, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 7)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Hooker Chemical / Ruco Polymer, Nassau County, 1993; 1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 8)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Huntington Landfill, Huntington, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 9)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Islip Landfill Site (Blydenburgh), Hauppauge, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 10)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Jameco Industries, Wyandanch, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 11)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Li Tungsten Corporation Site, Glen Cove, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 12)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Liberty Industrial Finisihing, Farmingdale, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 13)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Long Beach Incinerator, Long Beach, 1992-1997 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 14)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Mattiace Petrochemical Company Site, Glen Cove, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 15)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Nassau Tool Works, Babylon, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 16)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, New Cassel Industrial Area, North Hempstead, 1996-1998; 2 folders (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 17-18)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, North Sea Municipal Landfill, Southampton, 1992-1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 19)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, NTU Circuits, Bayshore, 1991-1996; 3 folders (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 20-22)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Old Bethpage Landfill, Oyster Bay, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 23)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Old Roosevelt Air Field Hanger Site, Hempstead, 1995-2002 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 24)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Port Washington Landfill, North Hempstead, 1982-1995 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 25)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Preferred Plating Corporation, Farmingdale, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 26)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Pyridium Mercury Disposal Sites, Harriman, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 27)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Roanoke Sand and Gravel, Middle Island, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 28)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 1, Smithtown Groundwater Contamination Site, Smithtown, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 29)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 2, Fresh Kills Landfill, Staten Island, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 30)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 2, New York City, 1983-2003 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 31)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 2, Bronx Lebanon Hospital / BFI Regional Medical Waste Incinerator, Bronx, 1996-1999; 2 folders (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 32-33)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 2, Carol Cleaners, Staten Island, 1994-1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 34)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 2, Levco Metal (s) Finishing, Astoria, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 35)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Dabroski vs. Newburgh Packing Corporation, Newburgh, 1992-1994; 2 folders (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 36-37)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Mercy College C&D Debris Landfill / The Landing at Dobbs Ferry, 1990-2000; 2 folders (Box 1 (1-Activities), Folder 38-39)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, 1985-2005; 3 folders (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 1-3)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Bernal Well, Germantown, 1982-1986 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 4)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Grant Hardware, West Nyack, 1988-1997 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 5)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Harbor at Hastings, Hastings-on-Hudson, 1998-1999 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 6)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, IBM Sites, 1995 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 7)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Kay - Fries Inc., Stony Point, 1992-1997 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 8)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Kessman / Cross County Landfill, Patterson, 1989-2002 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 9)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Keuffel & Esser (K&E), Taconic Products, Millerton, 1991; 1993 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 10)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Le May Optical Company, Kent, 1980-1989 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 11)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Marathon Battery Company, Cold Spring, 1985-1991 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 12)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Napanoch Paper Mill, Napanoch, 1988-1992 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 13)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, New Windsor Soil Burners, New Windsor, 1993-1997 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 14)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Old Nyack/Dexter Landfill/Pyramid Mall Project, West Nyack, 1974-1995; 4 folders (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 15-18)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Prisco C&D/Hazardous Substance Dump, Patterson, 1988-1998; 2 folders (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 19-20)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, SUNY New Paltz, 1992-1993 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 21)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Ramapo Town Landfill, Ramopo, 1986-1993 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 22)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Retron-Woodstock, Woodstock, 1995-2002 (Box 2 (1-Activities), Folder 23)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Wallkill Landfill, Wallkill, 1992-1994 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 1)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Westchester County Airport, Harrison, 2002-2003 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 2)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Revere Smelting and Refining (RSR) Corporation, Wllkill, 1994-1996 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 3)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 3, Tuxedo Landfill, Tuxedo, 1987-1989 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 4)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, 1983-2003 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 5)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, BASF, Rensselaer, 1985-2004 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 6)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Campbell Plastics, Rotterdam / Schenectady, 1999 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 7)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Coeymans Landfill, Coeymans, 1995-2004 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 8)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, County Maps, 1995-1996 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 9)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Dewey Loeffel Landfill, Nassau, 1997-2005; 4 folders (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 10-13)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, East Greenbush Landfill, East Greenbush, 1983-1998 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 14)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Frisbie Avenue, Albany, 1990 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 15)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, GE Selkirk / Various, 1987-1993 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 16)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Jet - Line Services, Scotia / Glenville, 1989 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 17)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, M. Wallace & Son, INC., Cobleskill, 1994-1996 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 18)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Mercury Refining, Inc., Colonie, 1982-1994 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 19)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Montgomery - Oswego - Schoharie Solid Waste Management Authority (MOSA), 1996-1998 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 20)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, New Options on Waste, Inc., Albany, 1995-1997 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 21)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Niskayuna Landfill, Niskayuna, 1987-1988 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 22)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, N.L. Industries, Colonie, 1985-1996 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 23)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Norlite Corporations, Cohoes, 2005 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 24)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Pedone Landfill, Glenville, 1988-1996 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 25)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Rotterdam Landfill, Rotterdam, 1997-1999 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 26)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Route 146A Barrel Site, Clifton Park, 1982-1991 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 27)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Sand Lake Landfill, Sand Lake, 1986-2000 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 28)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Waite Road, Clifton Park, 1982-1990 (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 29)
    - Hazardous Waste Sites, DEC Region 4, Regional Outreach, 1981-2002; 2 folders (Box 3 (1-Activities), Folder 30-31)